<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Critical remarks upon the adventures of Telemachus son of Ulysses· Translated from the French.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80828</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6960A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224553</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897195</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897195</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132844</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80828)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132844)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2478:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Critical remarks upon the adventures of Telemachus son of Ulysses· Translated from the French.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for H. Rhodes, at the Star the corner of Bride-lane, and A. Bell, at the cross Keys in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mythology, Greek --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132844:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Critical REMARKS Upon the ADVENTURES OF <hi>TELEMACH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> Son of ULYSSES.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated from the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Rhodes,</hi> at the Star the corner of <hi>Bride-lane,</hi> and <hi>A. Bell,</hi> at the croſs Keys in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:132844:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:132844:2"/>
            <head>Critical REMARKS Upon the ADVENTURES OF <hi>Telemachus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN truth, Sir, you are a dangerous Enemy; 'tis neither fair nor civil to take ſo much Advantage of the Power ye have over me. I have my Reaſons for my Silence; why ſhould you urge me to Garrulity? I tell you over and over again, all People look upon <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemachus</hi> to be an admirable Piece: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did Hero appear upon the Stage with ſuch an univerſal Applauſe. 'Tis witty, delicate, natural, 'tis myſterious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanting; what would you have more? Oh! but ſay you, I do not ask your Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents about the reliſh of the Publick; I am ſufficiently inform'd of the great
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:132844:3"/>noiſe which this little Romance makes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the curious; 'tis the Subject Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mode for Converſation; but I deſire to know you Thoughts concerning it. To what an inconveniency do you expoſe me? I muſt now be lookt upon in your Judgment for a ridiculous Manhater, if I cannot diſcover in this Piece, thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Beauties that charm all other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Am I not already ſufficiently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate, to be poſeſs'd with a croſs thwarting Humour, but that I muſt be oblig'd my ſelf to reveal my own Shame? All the World admires <hi>Telemachus;</hi> on the other ſide, I that can find nothing in it worthy Admiration, yet do my ſelf this Juſtice, for my want of a good Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, that I admire my own Stupidity. This I take to be an ingenious way of ſhifting off the Condemnation of the Piece; and any other Perſon but your ſelf would diſcharge me, after ſuch a Confeſſion. You might blame me for my want of Judgment, without putting your ſelf to the trouble of exacting my bad Reaſons. But I know your Humour in reſpect of my ſelf; my fantaſtical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits divert yee, and you have done me the Honour to tell me, that you take ſome kind of delight to ſee me fencing with the Multitude. It ſhall not then be ſaid,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:132844:3"/>that 'tis long of my ill Nature, or <hi>Momus</hi>-like Temper that you are not ſatisfi'd. I will then faithfully Copy out the Idea which I have fancy'd to my ſelf of the famous <hi>Telemachus,</hi> and give you leave to Laugh, upon condition that you laugh in a corner alone. I have but three Aſſaults to make upon this impregnable Fortreſs. I ſhall firſt examin the deſign that ſent <hi>Telemachus</hi> abroad into the World; in the next place, I muſt attack the Style of this ingenious Fiction: And laſtly, I ſhall endeavour to unfold the meaning of this ſame Satyr, altogether Myſtical, which as ſome will have it, the Author has with ſuch a zealous Devotion diſplay'd againſt the Wiſeſt and moſt Potent Government that ever was.</p>
            <p>Now then, that I may make my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, as all others do (for I muſt tell you, I have no other foundation to aſſure my ſelf either of the Name or Intentions of the Author) The aim of the Work is Great, Noble and Lofty: To teach a young Prince the pureſt Maxims of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to ſet Vice before his Eyes in all the hideous ſhapes of it, to make him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the lovely ſweets of Vertue, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe in his Ears a thouſand and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times over, that Wickedneſs is the cauſe of all Misfortunes, and that Juſtice
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:132844:4"/>is the Fountain of all Happineſs; to form his Mind according to the moſt lively Lights of Knowledge and Underſtanding; to render his Heart impenetrable againſt all Irregularity, this is to conceive a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to raiſe his Royal Pupil to the Pina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Glory, and to procure the Felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the People, who are one Day to live under the Dominion of this young Prince. But with your good leave, has this deſign been put in execution, in ſuch a manner as to promiſe good Succeſs? For my part, had I an intention to ſpoil a young Inclination, I would give ſuch a Youth <hi>Telemachus</hi> for his Pocket Book. Nor can I diſapprove the Raillery of a Courtier, who was ſaying t'other Day, that if the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> were wholly guided by this Romance, the Crown of <hi>France</hi> would be in danger of falling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Government of a Diſtaff. They with whom he was joaking, underſtood no other wit in his Jeſt, but that he meant <hi>Minerva</hi> in diſguiſe. But he drove higher, as I underſtood from one of his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance; for his meaning was, that if ever a <hi>Telemachus</hi> raign'd, under the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpices, and by the Counſels of ſuch a ſevere Goddeſs, Viſion, Chimera, and Fanaticiſm would ſit upon the Throne. If you gueſs, as I make no queſtion but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:132844:4"/>you do, at the Brain that was deliver'd of this Fancy of a Romance, beware of revealing it: For in jeſting with Jupiters Wiſdom, you would ruin the Reputation of a judicious Man, which an illuſtrious Friend has acquir'd in the World; there would not be a Wit o'th'Town but would be ready to throw a Stone at him, and all would cry out, that 'twould be better for them to be lodg'd in a Mad-houſe than in his great Palace. But ſince 'tis yours and my Profeſſion not to judge of things by the common reliſh, let us weigh his Proofs, and ſee who is in the right, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he or all Mankind beſide. You your ſelf have told me a Hundred times, that the Labours of Fiction are poyſon'd Springs, from whence young People know not how to draw, without intereſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Exactneſs of Diſcernment, and and without receiving dangerous Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions againſt the uprightneſs of the Soul. Poets and Writers of Romances never ſpeak like other Men, being forc'd to follow another Road then that of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to arrive at that ſublimity which they ſeek for in themſelves, they overdo what ever they go about. The Fire of Imagination, in them, ſupplies the place of profound Reaſoning. But reduce theſe pompous Deſcriptions, theſe glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:132844:5"/>Images, this refin'd <hi>Tour</hi> to the Terms of good Senſe, 'tis only the flaſh of the Powder that has paſs'd before your Eyes, and leaves nothing behind but the ill ſcent. Nature and Truth are in the Hands of theſe Gentlemen to be dawb'd, and fucuſs'd over as much as they ſhall think proper for their own Purpoſes: Never believe that they preſent before us thoſe two Countenances with that ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity which is their principal Ornament. They are aſham'd to ſay with the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, that the Sun riſes and ſets; that it has been a plentiful Harveſt; that the Meadow is cover'd with Flowers; that the Water is clear; that the Trees are laden with Fruit. Pitiful Expreſſions that wou'd make thoſe inſpir'd Enthuſiaſts bluſh There is a much more noble elevation of Wit to be made uſe of in explaining to us the Motions of Nature, under the ſublime Emblems of Dewy Charies, Chryſtal, Pearls, Diamonds, and all thoſe other pretty Toys of which our <hi>Telemachus</hi> is a true Magazine. Is he to commend a good Prince? He is exempt from all humane Infirmities; his Merit ſurpaſſes Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and he has perform'd thoſe At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements for which there want exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in Story; and the Vertue of that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro is as inconceivable as <hi>Pure Love.</hi> It is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:132844:5"/>his buſineſs to cenſure the Conduct of an ill King? there's no mercy to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he is a Tyrant; he has made unjuſt Wars; he has broken Faith with his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates; in the midſt of Peace he has ſurpris'd 'em, pillag'd their Cities, burnt their Houſes under ridiculous pretences; he has violated his Oaths, ruin'd his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; he has invaded the Rights of God, oppreſs'd his moſt faithful Subjects; he has openly juſtifi'd Adultery; he is a monſter abandon'd to his own Obduracy; 'tis in vain for him to have recourſe to the Gods, they are inexorable to his Prayers; their anger is juſt ready to thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon his Head; Monſieur the Poet has pronounc'd the Decree, nor will he bate a tittle of the Sentence. Well, Sir, what do you think ont? d'ye believe a young Prince to be well plae'd in the Hands of ſuch a ſort of Guides? Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times climbing to the top of a Mountain, ſometimes deſcending to the bottom of a Valley; never moving upon even Ground; to have always a ſlippery Ice before their Eyes; call you this an eaſy Road to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive happily at a Throne? To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is it to create an imaginary World in order to teach a young Prince how to reign in ours? Our Kings are not like Kings upon a Theatre, who only enter up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:132844:6"/>on the Stage to repreſent fabulous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; They ought to govern according to the Laws, and according to the preſent time, and this is that wherein they ought to be inſtructed, without fetching compaſſes about, and the refinement of Hyperboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Language. You will not deny but that Kings have more need of Judgment and Penetration then other Men, for they ſuffer themſelves too frequently to be ſurpriz'd by prejudice; and that crowd of Flatterers which environs 'em is a Rail that Truth has much ado to leap over. How then is it poſſible for a young Prince to walk in a hazardous Country, where he runs from Phantom to Phantom, from falſhood to falſhood, where he meets with none but Objects capable to ſeduce a better inſtructed Reaſon then his own? Did you never ſpend a ſerious thought, Sir, upon theſe Portraictures ſo flattering and ſo apt to tickle the Senſes? I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain you would never, upon ſuch Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, expoſe ſuch charming deluſions to the Eyes of your Family, much leſs, if you have been call'd to the Prelature, would you do it to any other Perſon. What ſhall we ſay of thoſe Courteſans of Goddeſſes, amourous even to Tranſport, penſive, jealous, reſtleſs, furious, and ſometimes driven to diſpair? The devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132844:6"/>of the <hi>Cretan</hi> Women for <hi>Venus</hi> and her Pleaſures? the Paſſion of <hi>Calypſo</hi> to captivate <hi>Telemachus</hi> in her golden Treſſes, and the fruitleſs Toyls of <hi>Cupid</hi> to the ſame purpoſe? You may look upon theſe things as Trifles if you pleaſe, but in my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, the leading of a young Prince in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe ſlippery places, is in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to couple his Mind with Superſtition, and expoſe his Heart to dangerous At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks; for in ſhort, what a ſtrange me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod is it for the inſtructing of a Chriſtian Soul, to teach it down right Paganiſm, to carry a Diſciple into inchanted Places with an intent to infuſe into him an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of Pleaſure, to expoſe him to violent Temptations, with a deſign to render his Innocence invincible? This is the utmoſt that a conſummate Quieteſt durſt preſume to undertake; and yet perhaps, he would find a neceſſity of intrenching himſelf well before hand in his paſſive Condition, to digeſt his Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and to prevent his conſenting to the ſweet impreſſions of Objects. But youth is not ſufficiently harden'd to thoſe inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Combats, to be led after ſuch a manner into the Fire: We know it has a far greater inclination to Vice then of Vertue: It needs no encouragement to idolize Pleaſure; rather, unleſs it be of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132844:7"/>an extraordinary Temper, what ſhould incite him to deſpiſe it? The reaſon of a young Man is not ripe enough for Truth; Age and Experience are abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to convince him of thoſe noble and great reſemblances and agreements where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Truth conſiſts: But has the Senſe of a young Man ſufficient Vigour to reſiſt the Allurements of Voluptuouſneſs? Now then to expoſe before a young Prince the view of Pleaſure almoſt ſtark naked, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence that it unfolds the Truths of Salvation and Morality, what is this but to enervate his Mind by flattering his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions? rather is it not as if a Phyſician ſhould give Poyſon to a feeble Stomach, to procure the digeſtion of ſtrong Food? Is not this to corrupt at the ſame time that he pretends to inſtruct? This is but a bad ſort of Pedagogie; however it is <hi>Telemachus</hi> all over. <hi>Mentor</hi> ſpeaks the nobleſt things in the World, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it; but the Author with his Roman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Chain of yolle Stories, deſtroys the virtue of the Exhortations, like an old Dotard as he is. <hi>Mentor</hi> preaches up one Holy God, Almighty, Immenſe, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, and Adorable; the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor teaches a company of vicious Deities, bounded in their Power; Vagabonds, familiar, ignorant and paſſionate. <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:132844:7"/>corroborates the heart againſt Sloth and Female tenderneſs; the Author does all he can to render it Effeminate. <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> makes Happineſs to conſiſt in Vertue; the Author makes it always unfortunate, and introduces the wicked always happy till Death. <hi>Mentor</hi> would have a King to be juſt, and that he ſhould Sacrifice himſelf for the welfare of his People; the Authors Hero's are two Princes, one of which abandons his Subjects to revenge the Quarrel of a Miſtreſs; the other Scap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erloiters about the World like a Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb, leaving his Mother and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try a Prey to a company of Rivals. The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel would make you ſtare, ſhould I car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it as far as I could ſtretch it. Stay but till I examin the Tomes apart, and you ſhall have more pleaſant Encounters to make you merry. In the mean time I beſeech yee allow me one thing; That this Piece being an Ambiguous Contexture of Piety and Superſtition, of Error and Truth of Figure and Natural, of Vice and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, of good and bad Senſe, it favours the Inclination of a young Prince to Evil, and is only fit to perplex and confound his Ideas of Good. But here you will object and cry, this is all but ſlaſhing the Air. He that proves too much proves nothing: According to your Concluſions, Youth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:132844:8"/>muſt be excluded from reading the Poets, and all manner of Fictions, and then the Lord have Mercy upon yee; for all the Regents of Colledges, and Maſters of Schools, would fall about your Ears, and thoſe Pedantick People are a terrible ſort of Enemies, who are always in Arms, and their Laſhes will fetch Blood through a Quire of Brown Paper. Well, Sir, let 'em be as terrible as they pleaſe, their Menaces are not able to terrify me. Thanks to my evil Deſtiny, I fear neither Eagles nor Crows. But you miſtake the ſenſe of my Sentiments, and therefore for your better information, let us argue a little after the venerable manner of the Schools. I offer yee this Propoſition. A prudent Tutor ought not, on purpoſe to compoſe a Romance interwoven with Sacred and Prophane, to form the Mind and Heart of a young Prince: From whence you conclude, that all Poetry is pernicious to young People. But this is no good Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick; for you argue from a Particular to a General. Tho' I had Learning, and Credit ſufficient to baniſh out of Colledges the Illuſion and Bombaſtical Style of Poetry, I would not deſire to merit the Name of a Reformer in the Republick of Learning: That Honour would be due to a Perſon who for Erudition and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licacy,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:132844:8"/>is none of the meaneſt Ornaments of the Age: You know who I mean. But I pretend not to go too far. I agree with whoſoever pleaſes to agree with me, that good Poetry may be profitable to Youth in many things; It is an Art that requires Application, and procures to the Wit a Felicity to unfold and penetrate many Difficulties. Salt and Poynancy, which are as it were the Soul of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Amuſement, afford Matter for that which is called <hi>Brilliant.</hi> Neither are Fictions barren Images; they ſerve to render the Wit inventive, and Invention is the Mother of publick Benefit. But what is all this to my Theſis? Is it leſs certain, that Poetry and Romances are two Rocks againſt which good Senſe and Vertue ſplit themſelves a thouſand times, and ſuffer Shipwrack? For which reaſon it is, that prudent Maſters will never let their Diſciples be out of their ſight when they give 'em leave to ramble that ſlippe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tract, ſo ſteep and full of Precipices. Have a care they cry, this Idea is falſe, that Conceit is poor and flaſhy, that piece of Morality is corrupt, that Example is to be abominated. We only paſs theſe Phantoms ſlightly before your Eyes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis fit you ſhould know every thing, and becauſe there is a neceſſity of ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:132844:9"/>to the Tyranny of Cuſtom. What would you think, Sir, after all this of a grave and devout Preceptor who ſhould bethink himſelf of rammaſſing all theſe Follies together, and incorporating 'em into one Romance, with an intention to infuſe-into a young Prince his Pupil, a ſolid Piety, Juſtice incorruptible, a Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence proof againſt all Tryal, a Courage unſurmountable, a right Senſe, and an exact Diſcernment; in a Word, all the Qualities that might render a King wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy his Diſtinction. A goodly Catechiſm you'll ſay, and preſently reply, ſuch a Guide would lay the Snare, dig the Ditch, and make the Bait himſelf. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, this is <hi>Telemachus</hi>'s deſign, if the publick have done him Juſtice. It may be you will be skirmiſhing with your Objections againſt me, and tell me that 'tis lawful for a Tutor to make uſe of his own Romances, as well as of thoſe which are compoſs'd by theirs, and that provided he order his Diſciples to read 'em with neceſſary precautions, nothing hinders but that his Wit may prove an Honour to him. But what you get by this you may put in your Eye. For a Tutor is made choice of to meet the miſchief, not to give occaſions for the growth of it. 'Tis his duty to weed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:132844:9"/>whatever may prove deſtructive to his young Plant, and not to ſet any thing near it, that may feed it with ill juice. This Tutor is the young Princes Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Phyſician, 'tis his Duty to let him know which are good, which are bad Nouriſhments; but if the Phyſician ſhould himſelf prepare dangerous Food for his Patient, in hopes to have the Honour of preventing the ill Conſequences of it, think you that would be well done? I am ſure, you do not belive that ſuch a man could act with a ſafe Conſcience; nor would you, if once it came to be known, diſcharge him upon a bare Repentance. Let us drive the Nail as far as it will go. <hi>Telemachus</hi> is a Compoſition of Fiction and Truth, of Vices and Vertues, of Good and Evill: The Tutor who is a Man Able, Eloquent, Perſwaſive and a profound My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick every Inch of him, employs all the ſtrength of his great Genius to hinder the young Prince from miſtaking his courſe between theſe two oppoſites. He makes him underſtand the Ridiculouſneſs of Ficton, the deformity of Evil, the beauty of Vertue, and the reputation that attends Men of worth: But who has told this <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> that his <hi>Alexander</hi> will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him upon his Word? If the young Prince be of a temper to be carried away
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:132844:10"/>with Hyperboles and Figures; If he be of a merciful Humour, not to let a fair Goddeſs dye for Love; If <hi>Cupid</hi> ſubdue him under the Empire of <hi>Venus;</hi> If he takes a liking to the Religion of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Craete;</hi> If the diſpoticiſm and avarice of <hi>Pygmalion</hi> do not offend him; And laſtly, If inſtead of taking out all the Honey of the Romance, he ſucks out all the Venom, Theres a young Prince quite ſpoil'd: and when he comes to be King, his Subjects muſt be miſerable; and all this will be charg'd to our Tutors account. Would you believe it, Sir, that this famous <hi>Telemachus,</hi> upon whom all People beſtow their Panegyricks, and ſtrew Flowers, that I may ſpeak like a Poet, by whole Baskets full, ſhould one day prove the cauſe of moſt diſmal effects, and conſequently become the Object of publick Malediction? I know that I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat with a Fly, and that the Misfortune will never happen: It may be <hi>Telemachus</hi> will be better advis'd then to turn Peda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue: But tho' he ſhould have aim'd at the Education of a Prince ſo well known to us, there would have been no danger. That Prince is too well born to turn to his ruin what was only compoſs'd for his preſervation: But in ſhort the thing is not impoſſible; and that is ſufficient for me
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:132844:10"/>to condemn the deſign which is aſcrib'd to the Work. In a Word, Sir, Why ſhould he not follow the beaten Road? Why ſhould not every Flower be gather'd from its own Bed? The true Method of inſtructing Youth is rightly to teach the diſtinction of Ideas, by never confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Matters. Every Inſtruction ought to be deriv'd from its own Spring: Let Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be drawn from the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; Mythology from Fables; The knowledge of Nature from Philoſophy; Actions from Hiſtory; And Morality from the World, which is the great Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume. Upon theſe different Subjects let 'em a Gods name, make as many and as long Commentaries as they ſhall judge convenient; but let it be done without anticipating one matter by another. For if you once confound 'em, you make a Gallimawfrey that diſtracts the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Diſciple; and while you go about to teach him all at a time, he learns nothing as he ought to do. From whence there is ſo much the more reaſon why great, Capital, and Eſſential Truths ſhould never be inſerted in Romances. In good earneſt, this is to enchaſe precious Stones in pitiful guilded Clay: Thoſe falſe Adventures are recounted with an Air of ſincerity, exact Circumſtances,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:132844:11"/>and all the appearances of Truth. Which way now to prevent a Youth from being deceiv'd? If he believes 'em, he's in a fair way to miſtake Error for Truth. Is he then capable of thoſe ſublime Speculations and of thoſe noble Maxims which they endeavour to infuſe into him? If he be apprehenſive of the Fiction, he ſtands upon his guard againſt ſurprize. He reads thoſe things which are leaſt ſubject to contradiction, as thoſe things which are moſt remote from good Senſe. So that in a well continu'd Romance, and Pieces well knit together, ſuch as is <hi>Telemachus,</hi> Falſhood becomes an obſtacle to Truth, and Truth inclines the Reader to believe the Falſhood. Would you know to whom I compare <hi>Mentor</hi> in the frequent Exhortations which he gives <hi>Telemachus?</hi> Even to an Orator that never would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce any other then falſe Panegyricks, nor ever would explain himſelf but by falſe Texts. For example, Sir, <hi>Mentor</hi> preaches like a Doctor in Romances: He raiſes ſome Perſons to the very Skies, and throws down others to the bottom of Hell: There is not one action that he praiſes but what is invented; nor is there any one which he condemns which is not Chymerical, what credit is there then to be given to theſe charming Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:132844:11"/>When he Dogmatizes like a <hi>Plato,</hi> Moralizes like a <hi>Socrates,</hi> and Diſcourſes like a <hi>Cato,</hi> concerning the Happineſs and Liberty of the People, they are like Struc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures without a Foundation: They are Conſequences which being erroneous in the firſt Principle, fall and themſelves de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy themſelves. For example, behold an Inference of <hi>Mentors</hi> Morality. Such and ſuch were happy or miſerable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, they did ſo and ſo; therefore it concerns you as you value your Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and would avoid Misfortune, to do ſo or ſo. Should the Diſciple anſwer, ſuch and ſuch were neither Happy nor Miſerable but in your Imagination; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is nothing real or ſolid in your Precepts; What ſhall the Maſter ſay? Well, while he is conſidering of it, I tell ye what I think of the Style of this Piece.</p>
            <p>You gueſs no doubt, Sir, what I drive at; and knowing my Genious ſo well as you do, 'tis eaſy for you to imagine that I am clearly out of conceit with this ſort of Poetical Proſe. I do not pretend to refineneſs of Wit; you are in the right on't, I admire, as another Man would do, when I am ſpoken to plainly and Politely, provided they ſpeak to me in the Language of Mankind, as three fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Writers in your <hi>Holland</hi> very lucki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:132844:12"/>do. But when Men pretend to diſorder all Nature, never to name an Object with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Figure or a <hi>Phoebus</hi> at the end of it, my language ſeems ſo barbarous that I'm at a ſtand whether I ſhall acknowledge it any longer or no. The Poets boaſt, that their Language is the Language of the Gods. In good truth, they ſpeak better then they are aware of; for from this Confeſſion we may conclude, that neither mortal Men underſtand them, nor that they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand themſelves. However, if they have receiv'd by infuſion the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what they write, let 'em write for the Gods as much as they pleaſe; Let 'em walk upon Stilts; Let 'em heap Fiction upon Fiction; Let 'em deſcend from their high flow Jargonry; Let 'em climb up to the Clouds; Let 'em immure themſelves within the narrow limits of Meaſure, Number, and Cadence, we have nothing to ſay to 'em. Theſe are a ſort of Birds that make uſe of their Wings to fly to <hi>Parnaſſus:</hi> the beauty of their Plumage is as reall as the Divinity of <hi>Apollo.</hi> Thats nothing to the purpoſe; theſe Birds have the priviledge to ſupport themſelves in the Air; let 'em enjoy it; theres nobody envies 'em their Happineſs; But let 'em not infect the Earth with their Viſions and their Dreams; Let 'em not intrude
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:132844:12"/>among us to ſet Mankind and good Senſe together by the Ears. 'Tis not juſt that falſhood ſhould cloath it ſelf in the Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Truth, for then what way will there be to diſtinguiſh the one from the other? Proſe is the natural means that Men make uſe of to communicate their Ideas one to another, to open their Hearts and intermix their Souls; it is the Vehicle of the light and warmth of Wit, as the Air is the conveyance of the Light and heat of the Sun. Through this the Sciences are transfus'd; by this the Laws are publiſh'd and obſerv'd, Equity ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, and Sincerity maintains it ſelf. 'Tis the Language of Society; nor do I know any People in the World that expreſs themſelves, that Reaſon, that Inſtruct one another or govern in Verſe. 'Tis upon this Ground, as I believe, at leaſt I do not know a better, that among clear ſighted People there is ſo much pains taken to poliſh the Language of the Country: they pare off the mean, impure, exceſſive and too much figur'd Expreſſions: The People are deſirous to think nothing but what is ſolid, they are willing to ſpeak as they think, and they are in the right on't. It may be, 'tis in this Senſe that our Authors are ſo ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous about the leaſt Rhime, and that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:132844:13"/>when they write, they will ſtiffe a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Words, as proper as they are to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their thought, ſo ſoon as they have found another that will better ſuit with the Cadence, tho' not ſo well with the Senſe: I know not whether you have ever examin'd the Reaſon of this nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but if you will believe Monſieur <hi>Jourdain,</hi> a great Maſter in Philoſophy, 'tis becauſe all that is Verſe is not Proſe, and all that is Proſe is not Verſe. But I know this Gibberiſh will not paſs in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with you for current Money. I am then rather willing to believe, that it proceeds from hence, that Proſe being only compos'd to cleare the Wit, and perſwade good Senſe, it cannot indure any thing that flatters the Ear, or tickles the Imagination. Upon this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Sir, does not your Heart riſe againſt the Verſify'd Proſe of <hi>Telemachus?</hi> When the Author of that Romance diſplays be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yee, in his ſimple and natural Style, yet grave and Majeſtick, thoſe fabulous Beauties fit only to amaze Fools, or to divert Children, tell me truly, d'yee find one once of that ſolidity which you ſearch for through the whole Piece? Rather are you not ſeiz'd with a ſecret Indignation that a Man ſhould employ a Language that is admir'd and ſpoken in almoſt all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:132844:13"/>the Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> in ſuch Foppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries as thoſe? Could it be poſſible that a Prelate who reaſons ſo profoundly upon Coeleſtial Verities, that neither the Pope nor the King, nor the Biſhops under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him, ſhould conſecrate his Pen to copy out in ſerious Proſe the Chimera's of the Poets and the moſt abominable Superſtitions of Paganiſm? How was it poſſible for a compleat Quietiſt, when he was compoſing ſo prophane a Piece, to preſerve a ſight of God, acting imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately upon the Faculties of the Soul? Could the Preſence of God inſpire him to paint forth a Lye, with a laborious Pencil in the Colours of Truth? Had the Author wrote in Verſe, he could not have been altogether excuſable, but there might have been leſs Cauſe to blame him. 'Tis true, that he could never have eſcap'd the Reproach of having miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent his leiſure Hours, in having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour'd his Profeſſion; and having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted myſtical Contemplation by vain Amuſements. But in ſhort the Reader, having perceiv'd the Stile of the Fiction could have been in no danger of a Surprize; 'twould have been taken for a Sport of Wit and Devotion incompati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with innocent Diverſion. But to counterfeit an idolatrous Hiſtorian, to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:132844:14"/>compoſe a Romance, repreſenting Truth under the Fabulous Action of Perſons exclaim'd againſt in Pulpits, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded in private Confeſſions, truly the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration was not myſtical, neither does it ſavour at all of the <hi>Interiour Man.</hi> Stop a little, ſay you, you run too faſt — What! d'you rank <hi>Telemachus</hi> among the <hi>Caſſandra</hi>'s, <hi>Claelia</hi>'s, <hi>Cyrus</hi>'s and <hi>Aſtrea</hi>'s? Yes, without Queſtion: — Where would you have had me plac'd him bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? I muſt confeſs that Wedlock is not the thing that is aim'd at there: But it is not for that Reaſon your devout People have thunder'd down theſe ſort of Books. If Romance be a Serpent, the Venom lies not in the Tayl, it always ends in Conjugal Union: — Nothing is more Civil nor more Natural. Where lies the Poyſon then? — Is it not in the Intrigues, and tender Movements, the amorous Impatiences — and Copulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons obtain'd with ſo much Myſtery — carry'd on with ſo much Secrecie, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd with ſo much Paſſion, and, in a Word, in the Management of their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour? How could an Amorous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce be deſcrib'd after a more ſenſible Manner, then it is done in <hi>Telemachus?</hi> What is there wanting to delight a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, who has a tender Heart? The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:132844:14"/>the Rendezvouzes, the Ejacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of Impatience uſual in other <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances,</hi> are they not to be found there. 'Tis true, there is no revealing there of ſecret Favours. But as you very well know, Romantick Lovers are much more diſcreet then Common Lovers; for their Authors will not let them commit an Error. They are not like the French who never think 'emſelves fully happy, unleſs they publiſh their good Fortune to all the World; beſides that <hi>Telemachus</hi> might ſteal ſomething from his dear Nymph, and never let Men know of it. No, Sir, call me Obſtinate and Incredulous as long as you pleaſe, I will never agree to the Sentiments of the Public. The Public, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Reſpect that I owe it, is a Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biter. 'Tis not poſſible, that a Myſtic ſhould be ſuch an Artiſt in making Love, tho' it was a pure Amour, intended only to lawful Enjoyment. There is too great an Oppoſition between Sacred and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Love. Sacred Love is without In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and without return of Reward. on the other ſide, Prophane Love is not ſatisfi'd with the Pleaſure of Loving; his Generoſity is intereſted, there muſt be a Reciprocal Return of Body and Soul. What likelihood then, that a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:132844:15"/>Prelate, ſwallow'd up in the Diſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtment of Divine Love, ſhould under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſo well the petty Traffic of Lovers? A Quietiſt lives at Reſt without Action; bur two Hearts that love each other are always in Motion. No, believe me, 'tis not the great Arch-Biſhop, who is the Author of <hi>Telemachus;</hi> and could I write with ſo much eaſe, as I have Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration for his Merit, I would ſtoutly undertake his Defence and write his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology, though I ran the hazard of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Lye given me by all that knew the contrary. But to return to my Text, for I perceive that I ſwerv'd a little too far from it; 'tis yet more contrary to good Sence, that ſuch a ſublime, judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Wit, ſo exact and wonderful in his Reliſh, ſhould bethink himſelf in our Age to continue the Rhapſodie of <hi>Homer,</hi> and gives us in Proſe a true O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliopodrido of Poetrie. Pardon me the Expreſſions; for here it is that I find my Wrath a little inflam'd; inſomuch that I could wiſh my ſelf Proctor Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Nation, that I might have the Liberty to proſecute the Author. I would ſummon him to appear before the Tribunal of Good Sence, that he might be fairly and duly condemn'd to ſtand in a white Sheet, with a Torch
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:132844:15"/>in his Hand, for the Honour of the French, with a Prohibition never to relapſe, and put his Country-Men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Temptation of changing Wit like the the Faſhions, and to quit a good Taſt for a bad Reliſh: What, d'ye laugh? You talk at your eaſe with your Dutch Flegm. But 'tis in good earneſt that I am angry at this Minute, and without any other Form of Proceſs, I condemn <hi>Telemachus</hi> that is in my Study, to be burnt by all the common Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>France.</hi> How! <hi>Telemachus</hi> that was compos'd for the Education of the Duke of <hi>Burgundy!</hi> You miſtake ſure: The Author had another Deſign in his Head. As he has a great deal of Wit he had a mind to ſport with the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of <hi>France,</hi> and to divertiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alone behind the Curtain. Do not you call my Conjecture a Viſion; I ground it upon the Succeſs of the Work, and if the Author had built upon that Platform, he would have had all the Reaſon in the World to have been ſa, tisfi'd with his Deſign. 'Tis in Matter of Wit the French ſtrive to excel other Nations, in judging ſoundly of another Man's Works. They flatter themſelves that they enjoy by a certain Priviledge that happy Penetration which makes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:132844:16"/>them diſtinguiſh Solidity from falſe Luſtre. Never till now did they puſh on ſo far this pretended Delicacy of theirs. I know not whether it be with you in your Boggs as it is here. But 'tis a Pleaſure at <hi>Paris</hi> to ſee the Bookſellers Shops full of a Number of Cenſurers; who decide the Fate of Books like Oracles, and tell ye with an erected Eyebrow, this creeps, that clambers. We are come off from theſe Simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; why ſhould the Preſs be ſully'd with ſuch naſty Sotticiſms. Men are become altogether Men: they are no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger pleas'd with any thing but what is Natural and Judicious; we deſire ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that may inſtruct us, not amuſe us. Yet would you think it, Sir? theſe rigorous Judges are the greateſt Adorers of <hi>Telemachus.</hi> Thoſe lofty Wits take a ſingular Delight to ſee the Sun come forth from the Boſom of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous <hi>Theirs,</hi> bound from the Arms of his Miſtris to get into his Coach, at his leiſure make his <hi>Tour</hi> about the World drawn by his Free-breathing Streeds. <hi>Aurora</hi> appears charming to them in her <hi>Dewie Waine.</hi> — De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wie Wain! Mark that: Dew is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but drops of Water that fall from the Skie. Nevertheleſs thoſe Drops
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:132844:16"/>make a Waggon — How Natural that is? <hi>Venus</hi> goes to kiſs her Darling <hi>Papa,</hi> and conjures him with Tears in her Eyes, that he will be pleas'd that <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemachus</hi> may ſuffer himſelf to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd. The good <hi>Papa</hi> is mollifi'd; and but for cruel Deſtinie that gives him Laws, he would conſent that <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemachus</hi> ſhould become the greateſt Whore-maſter under the Skie. Theſe are but faint Sketches of the Beauties of <hi>Telemachus.</hi> If our Correſpondence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues, you ſhall ſee a great many more. How is it poſſible to cry down ſuch a Piece of Juicie and Florid Proſe! after this, talk no more of our French Men: It belongs only to them to aſpire to the Univerſal Monarchy of Wit. This brings a Fancy into my Head. The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of our incomparable Prince, have given out a long time that he was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting the Conqueſt of all <hi>Europe.</hi> The Calumny was too palpable. The King's Juſtice and Moderation is too well known, and his Majeſty has given illuſtrious Proofs of in, in ſtopping ſeveral times the Rapid Courſe of his Victorious Arms, and giving Peace to <hi>Europe:</hi> The Truth is this, that if <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great did not ſeek to be Maſter of <hi>Europe,</hi> he was very near being ſo, till Heaven,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:132844:17"/>whoſe Deſigns are profound, and who carries them on by ways unknown, rais'd as it were out of Nothing, another Prince that was capable of humbling a haughty Potentate, and diſappointing the vaſteſt of his Deſigns. There has ſomething of this Nature befall'n our Nation, prepoſſeſſ'd with her own Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, thro' the Succeſs with which they have cultivated the Liberal Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and all manner of Learning. She ſet up for an Arbitratrix of good Reliſh, arrogating to her ſelf a Prerogative to decide as a Sovereign, the Works of Wit, and pretending that nothing ought to paſs for good Sence, but what was ſeal'd with her Approbation. But an unknown Perſon comes and throws himſelf in the way, and not being able to endure ſo much Pride, it comes into his Head to bring her a Pegg lower. What does he do? Like an honeſt Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giarie, He Pillages the Poets; he pilfers a Dream from one, a wild piece of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage from another, to give a kind of Solidity to theſe hollow Imaginations; he dreſſes up a Fable Alamode; and let's it run about the Streets; preſently behold all the French Men at the heels of it: 'Tis in vain to cry, Stop: This Proſe is a Curtiſan in diſguiſe; her Dreſs
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:132844:17"/>has no reſemblance with what ſhe is. 'Tis the ſame that you chas'd and exploded with ſo much ignominy forty Years ago. No matter for that, ſhe talks better then ſhe did at that time; and her Language in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely pleaſes us. But ſhe ſtill repeats the ſame fooleries: Let it be ſo; ſhe plays the fool wittily; that's what we would have. Oh the excellent <hi>Genius</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! Have we not reaſon to reproach her for being fond of her Language, when ſhe prefers it before Truth and good Senſe? What reaſon has ſhe to laugh at the <hi>Swiſſes?</hi> They, good People, pay themſelves with words, and provided the Cadence pleaſes, never trouble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves about the figuification. Our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirers of <hi>Telemachus,</hi> do they not do the ſame thing? Let us talk with a little more Equity. A <hi>Swiſs</hi> never contta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts himſelf; he knows what he loves, and ſeeks it after his own manner. But the <hi>French</hi> who cry out every where for Subſtance, good Nouriſhment, good Juice, ſerve their Tables with painted Meſſes, and devour 'em. I excuſe this Tranſport in your Refugees: Not but that I believe 'em to be People of Wit, but their Souls are not in their natural ſcituation. Living as they do without Callings, without Eſtates, they ſtand in need of Amuſement,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:132844:18"/>and beſides that, ſince the time that you ſeparated from us, we may look upon ye as half Strangers. But that in <hi>Paris,</hi> the ſource of Illumination, the Country of Underſtanding, the Center of good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, they ſhould be ſo hungry after <hi>Tele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus,</hi> that they ſhould throw their <hi>Louidores</hi> at the Heads of the Bookſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, to carry away that Romance as a piece of value; I cannot in that reſpect acknowledge my ſelf for a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> and I'm afraid, that the Age of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt begins to decline in point of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which would be but a bad Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtication of the Continuance of the Monarchy. You will not fail to ask me here whither <hi>Mentor</hi> ſpoke <hi>Greek</hi> for me, and whither I could comprehend nothing of the Divine Leſſons, which that wandring Goddeſs gives at every end of the Field to her Favourite <hi>Telemachus?</hi> Yes, Sir, I underſtand 'em all very well, but I know not whither it procceded from the dulneſs of my Wit, or the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my Heart, I was not at all mov'd with 'em. <hi>Mentor,</hi> who is Wiſdom it ſelf, teaches his Diſciple to ſubject the Animal part of his Soul to the Spiritual part; to make himſelf Maſter of his Paſſions, to prefer Conſcience and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity before all things. What do you
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:132844:18"/>find ſo wonderful in all this? A petty School-maſter does it as well: Was this worth the trouble of proſtituting the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of <hi>Minerva,</hi> and making a Gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Huſwife of her, to tell him the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt and moſt common things in the World? The Author might have let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone that Daughter of <hi>Jupiter</hi> to enjoy the Advantages of her Birth in quiet, and have taken the firſt that came of the Clarks in his Dioceſs; I ſpeak only by way of ſuppoſition. I am ſure that with a little good Senſe, and eaſineſs to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs himſelf, he might have ſaid as much as the Divine Pedagogue. Wherein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the Excellency of that Morality which enchants the World ſo much? In continually repeating the ſame Precepts? I aſſure ye, that <hi>Mentor</hi> had great need of being a God, to ſucceed in his Perſwaſions: His Doctoral Style could not be thinner, He neither proves, nor demonſtrates the Effect by the Cauſe, nor the Cauſe by the Effect. All his Philoſophy is reduc'd to this ſmall Inference: They did this, and were commended, therefore you ought to do ſo too. They did this and were blam'd, therefore you ought to have a care how you follow their Example. Muſt a Man be cleft out of <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s Skull to ſay this? 'Tis true indeed, that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:132844:19"/>the fluency of the Words ſupplies the force of the Reaſoning. If it be true then, that a Judicious Reader be no Friend to a Conciſe Stile, then indeed I am too blame, to wonder that <hi>Telemachus</hi> is ſo much admir'd; for inſtead of including much Senſe in few words, 'tis much more when a pompous diſplay of words furniſhes us with a reliſh of good Senſe. The Miſchif is, that the ſame Expreſſions as frequently return as the ſame Things. Never was Man ſo wealthy in Synoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Terms; ſo that I would willingly adopt in his favour the Eulogy, which an Enemy of the Accademy formerly gave to a Member of that Illuſtrious Body. 'Tis ſaid he, the beſt dough of Man in the World, he has a number of words which boults and ſifts over and over again, with a wonderful Dexterity. But 'tis now high time that I ſhould have a fling at <hi>Tele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus</hi> for his Myſterious part; and I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with you, that this is the Part which makes his Reputation ſoar ſo high.</p>
            <p>My buſineſs, Sir, is here to penetrate the Intention of our Author. By all the Rules of Probity, my Criticiſm ought not to go ſo far; 'tis forbid me to grope ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man's Heart; 'tis a ſecret part, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd only for God, a Confeſſor, and a Confident. Tho' <hi>Mentor</hi> with his Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:132844:19"/>Exhortations ſhould viſit all the Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> that gives me no Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative to accuſe him of having a deſign upon any one. Suppoſe the King ſhould ſend to ask a great ſuſpected A. Biſhop, whether he had any deſign in <hi>Telemachu</hi> to cenſure the Governmen; there is no queſtion, but that laying his hand upon his Conſcience, and lifting up his Eyes to Heaven, he would reply, <hi>God forbid:</hi> and we ought to believe him upon his word. For Holy Men, and eſpecially Myſtical Holy Men, will never tell a Lye; ſo that had I nothing elſe to ſay to ye but that, the Myſtery will be at the bottom. But becauſe Men are wicked enough to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venom the Intentions of the moſt upright. and for that the Publick has been ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, as to report to our Court the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Declamations of <hi>Mentor</hi> againſt the Tyranny of bad Princes, I will leave the Author to his own Conſcience, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to root this malignity out of your mind. 'Tis very great; and I muſt frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge, that were they <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Polanders</hi> that were to interpret the Intention and diſcourſe of <hi>Mentor,</hi> I ſhould have nothing to object. Thoſe Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters of Liberty look upon us with an Eye of Scorn and Diſdain, and are ſtreight upon our Bones if we give Slavery the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:132844:20"/>leaſt good word. As for your Genlemen Reſugees, there's nothing elſe to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from them; exaſperated as they are againſt the King, it cannot be, but that the ſhadow of a Cenſute made by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout A. Biſhop muſt tickle their Hearts. You look upon your ſelves as Martyrs for the Cauſe of God and the Laws: And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if Patience, Charity, Humility, Piety and good Living were eminent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your People, your Faith would make the Conſcience of the moſt zealous Catholick tremble: But in ſhort, you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve your ſelves the Victims of an unjuſt Oppreſſion; 'tis no wonder then, you ſhould be ſo highly pleas'd with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever decrys the Conduct of your Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; in a word, I pardon you your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries and your Exultations over <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemachus:</hi> The leaſt favour that can be granted to Innocent Unfortunates; much leſs will I quarrel with your Brethren that languiſh in the midſt of us; their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune is ſtill greater then yours.</p>
            <p>But I have a ſecret Grudge againſt a Crowd of People, who boaſting to bear the glorious Titles of Catholick and French Men, prophane both the one and the other, by ſeeking in <hi>Telemachus</hi> the Cenſure of our Admirable Government: For I ought not to conceal our Shame:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:132844:20"/>it is certain, that <hi>Telemachus</hi> has run thro' <hi>France,</hi> with as much or more Applauſe as in <hi>Holland:</hi> and that which vexes me moſt is that they write me word from ſeveral Courts, that the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors make this Book their Favorite Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion; ſo that if what you ſend me word be true, that the worthy Miniſter that we have among you gave order that the Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller ſhould be well ſchool'd, I ſhall have a greater Eſteem for him then ever I had, and hope to thank him in the Name of all good French Men, ſo ſoon as he ſhall return. But don't you ſee, Sir, by this the Character of our Nation, without a Proſpective Glaſs; When the French Men do not love their King, they are inſolent; when they obey a Prince whom they adore, even to dotage, they are overjoy'd when he is revil'd and rayl'd at. But let us ſee whether there be any ground for the imagining that <hi>Mentor</hi> has done it in <hi>Telemaehus.</hi> For my own part, who am a little Scrupulous and who ſhould be very much troubl'd to think ill of my Neighbour, I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther believe that the Author of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, fill'd as he is, with veneration of our incomparable Monarch, has fetch'd a compaſs about to draw his Portraiture, and being unwilling to reſemble thoſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:132844:21"/>flattering Hiſtorians, who blind the Eyes of Princes with their Incenſe and their Smoak, he makes <hi>Minerva</hi> ſpeak in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral. To be ſhort, in all that <hi>Mentor</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folds to us of the Vettue, Glory and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of good Princes, is there any thing which does not preſently cauſe us to think of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV.? In the hideous, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Pictures that <hi>Minerva</hi> gives us of Tyrants, can we refrain our Joy when we conſider, that we have a Prince who is not ſo wicked as they? But you will not be fatisfi'd with an Idea ſo general. I know your Exactneſs; you muſt have a particular Accompt; <hi>go too then:</hi> The firſt and greateſt Quality that <hi>Mentor</hi> ſeeks in a good Prince is, that he ſhould live only for the ſake of his Subjects. Does not the King do ſo? 'Tis only out of a deſire to reign over his Subjects, that he deſires to live, and he will Reign to the laſt gaſp of his Breath, or elſe he would not be Maſter. <hi>Mentor</hi> would have it, that the Prince ſhould be the Father of his Country, and love his Subjects with as much tenderneſs as his own Children. Well, Sir, d' ye not ſee his Majeſty to the Life in all this? People judge of the Tenderneſs of a Father by his extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary zeal, to ſeek the good of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: Now I defie you and all your Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:132844:21"/>to find me out, ſince the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Royalty, a Prince that has longer and more ſucceſsfully apply'd himſelf, as well in Perſon as by his Miniſters, to ſeek the welfare of his Subjects; I mean their Spiritual and Temporal Welfare: and to prove it to ye, for with a <hi>Hugonot,</hi> we muſt be ſure to have good proofs for what we ſay; do not you conceive; Sir, that the true welfare of the People con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in Plenty? Riches perhaps are a more dangerous Enemy; they are only fit to enfeeble natural Vigour, to feed Paſſion and haſten Death. The chief Happineſs of Life is to be Maſter of his own Hearth, to eat his Bread in Peace under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of Juſtice: Now are not we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to the Kings Bounty for this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable Bleſſing? When he aſcended the Throne, he found Subjects that knew not how to make uſe of Fortunes Favours: Money was in their hands, like a Knife in the Hand of a Madman. Troubles, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, Rebellion was all the Talk of that Time: The Nobleman oppreſs'd the Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant; the Great men made the Little Ones turn about with the wind of their Pride and Capriccio; the Stronger gave Laws to the Weaker; From whence Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, Murders, Robberies, Injuſtice and Violence multiply'd; the People ſwel'd
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:132844:22"/>up with their own fat, no longer acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd any Maſter; or to ſpeak more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, they groan'd under the Yoke of an infinite number of petty Tyrants, &amp; forgot their Reſpect to their lawful Soveraign. The Princes, Governours, Parliaments, the Men in Credit, all theſe were like ſo many Flambeaux, that kindl'd and fed the Fire of Revolt, under the ſpecious pretence of maintaining the Law, and the preſervation of Liberty: Good Pleaſure, full Power and Soveraign Authority, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended upon all theſe Heads; and when Abuſes were to be reform'd, or Money was to be rais'd to ſupply the Publick Neceſſities, the Royal Majeſty was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to Affront or Refuſall. Our Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Father of his Country has pluck'd up all theſe Miſchiefs by the Roots, as a prudent Head of a Family ought to do: he has made himſelf Maſter of the whole. By that means his Kingdom is like a Houſe well regulated, where the Father diſpoſing of the whole Eſtate, retains every body in Order, in Subjection and in their Duty. Do we ſee any diſcontented Prince under <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, betake himſelf to Arms to do himſelf Juſtice? Do we ſee Governors draw whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces after 'em, contrary to the Intereſt of the Sovereign? Do we behold Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:132844:22"/>Libels preſented in an Aſſembly by the People's Deputies? Do we hear of any ſharp and Stinging Remonſtrances from a Parliament? So far from it, that the Ambition of Princes is calm'd, the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors are ſubmiſſive, the Parliaments ſet open their Regiſters, the People have no more to do but to open their Purſes; abſolute Power ſpreads its Influences eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, and every body libes in peace under his own Fig-tree. This Sir, is that; which among the Heroes is call'd ſeeking the Temporal good of the People. You <hi>Dutchmen</hi> with your ſhadow of Liberty, have no mind to agree to this. You look upon all us as Slaves and Beggars. 'Tis true our People are not ſo fat as yours, nor our Country Peaſants ſo rich: But if Murders and inſurrections ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen among you, is it not true, that you would wiſh to be in our places. Beſides, you are not to imagine that our Prince heaps up abundance and draws it to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to make a benefit of it, but to be a good Steward and a juſt Diſpenſer of it. Do you not ſee that he labours ſtill un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame Neceſſities, that his Edicts obſerve their Courſe, and that tho' he be actually at peace, he is conſtrain'd to augment the Taxes? What does he do, ſay you, with thoſe prodigious Numbers
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:132844:23"/>of Millions that go every Year into his Coffers? He generouſly divides a Part to thoſe who have the Honour to ſerve him, and principally to thoſe nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Head-pieces that manage the Finan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: He maintains ſormidable Armies that make him the Arbiter of the Laws, and the Terror of his Neighbours: He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larges his Palaces, and makes Embelliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments there, that ſurpaſs even wonder it ſelf: He reforms Nature, by levelling Hills and digging new Rivers. Has he not need of Immenſe Summs for thoſe incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Beauties, who had Charms ſufficient to engage his Heart, and oft refreſh'd him, wearied with the Toils of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? How many Cities purchas'd? How many Spies maintain'd abroad? I ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his famous Trafficking at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople;</hi> which if it were not the moſt famous of all, was yet the moſt beneficial to <hi>France.</hi> There is no need for me to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ye at this time how our great King has ſought, and ſtill ſeeks the Spiritual Welfare of his Subjects; you that are an Obſtinate Heretick know it too well: but the hardneſs of your Heart will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you to reap the Benefit of it; and this Pious Monarch ſtays but till the day of Judgment to reproach you with it. <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> would have a King be juſt; ours is ſo.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:132844:23"/>
            <p>He has made Reſtitution in earneſt, and reſtor'd to every one the beſt part of what belong'd to him. Juſt, do you ſay, to his People? Yes, juſter then to his Enemies? The ſame is <hi>Lewis</hi> the Grand: If we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by Juſtice that which is rendred in Tribunals; never Prince was ſo exactly careful in his Adminiſtration. He has tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out, and turn'd in all Officers of all ſorts and ſifted their Employments. He has created new ones in Superior and Inferior Juriſdictions; and if the Judges are the Eyes of a Prince, as ſome will have it, it may be ſaid without Flattery, that <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. is the moſt quick-ſighted among Monarchs. If we mean Juſtice that a King ought to render himſelf to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, 'tis that which our Prince never fail'd of. The French love Money, and when they have it can never live at quiet; they love Honour, and feed 'emſelves with it. What has our Prince done? He has taken away their Money, and given 'em Quiet and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in Exchange. Is not the one better then the other? The French love their Trade; but as a good Catholick People, they love their Religion better. The King has ſpoil'd Trade, but he has exterminated Hugnenotiſm, have the People any reaſon to complain? You ſhall hear a French Peaſant, that can hardly pay his Taxes,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:132844:24"/>chatting after his Ruſtical Manner, over a Pint of Wine of the King's Conqueſts and Victories; and then is he in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. I hold an even Wager, he would not change his Condition with one of the Burgo-Maſters. Had you ſeen, in the time of the War our Beggars dancing about a Bonfire, you would agree with me, that Poverty becomes a <hi>French</hi> Man, and that it is but Juſtice to reduce him to that Condition. But laſtly, one convining Proof of the King's great Juſtice is, that the People never complain. You who ſo regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly read the Gazette, have you ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd that the People cry out for Bread, or that they murmur'd at the ſcarcity of Money, or paſted up Paſquils, injurious to the Court? 'Tis true, the Gazetters and News Papers mention ſome ſuch thing ſometimes; but as we are not oblig'd to keep Faith with Hugnenots, ſo there is as little reaſon to credit 'em. <hi>Mentor</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims againſt unjuſt War; Is there any ſuch? The Right of War is authoriz'd by the Poſſeſſion of all Ages. <hi>Alexander</hi> is not quoted in Hiſtory for a Robber, nor the <hi>Romans</hi> for Uſurpers; were it ſo, the Pulpits would not ring ſo often as they do with their Names; and the Preachers would have a care how they ſuly'd their Sacred Eloquence, by extolling every
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:132844:24"/>Day thd Noble Actions of thoſe famous Conquerors. The King made uſe of this Right as another would have done. His Majeſty has extended his Frontiers, he has conquer'd Cities and Provinces, and acting with more ſincerity then thoſe ancient Lords of the World, who took all and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd nothing, the King has reſtor'd more then he took, and has kept nothing but what he could not reſtore. But who told theſe Interpreters of <hi>Telemachus</hi> that our King ever undertook an unjuſt war. Let 'em conſult all the Declarations of War that have been publiſh'd ſince the King's Marriage; I am ſure they will not find one that does not contain a great deal of Reaſon. That concerning bad Satisfaction which one of our illuſtrious Deſerters ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd among you with his uſual Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, is may be the weakeſt of all. But they who penetrate the Reaſons of that bad Satisfaction, agree that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint was not altogether ill grounded.</p>
            <p>You ſee then that <hi>Telemachus</hi> is not more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in his Myſterious Part, then in his Deſigns and his Stile. But to give ſomething to the Publick; I ſuppoſe with them, that <hi>Mentor</hi>'s Politicks are the Reverſe of the Government, and that 'tis that which has caus'd the diſgrace of the <hi>A.</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cambray.</hi> Do you not believe with my ſelf, that <hi>Mentor</hi>'s King is a Fantaſtic King, and that if Princes would reign according to the Memoirs of that old Dr. <hi>Minerva</hi> muſt have
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:132844:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>deſcended to the Earth to overturn the World. If a King ſhould obſerve all thoſe divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, he would become a Victim to his People, and his Condition would be worſe then that of a private Perſon; I wiſh all Nations one of <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi>'s Prince: but where will you find him: <hi>Mentor</hi> would have a King without Infirmities and Paſſions: Is this poſſible; King's being Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and always Fleſh and Blood, 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible but that they ſhould be ſubject to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Vices. An ambitious King ruines his People by War. A voluptuous Prince can give no good Example. A covetous King will ſuck the Blood of his Subjects. A Heart of Iron will never be mov'd to Compaſſion. A proud and deſpotick Prince will domineer over all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. A Prince prejudicated with a falſe Zeal will perſecute to death; and ſo of other Defects. 'Tis for the People to lay down their Necks, and bear the Burden. Theſe, Sir, are the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Remarks which I have made in Reading your <hi>Telemachus.</hi> You will hence conclude, that there is no great Matter in the Piece, or that I am but a Novice in theſe Matters. However, I ſhall comfort my ſelf with a full Perſwaſion, that I have ſaid nothing but what is true, and with the delight which I ſhall take in having obey'd your Orders. If you think fit, burn this little Epiſtle, and take a ſpecial Care that no Refugee may ſee it. Thoſe Gentlemen never love the Apologiſts of our Court; and as I have a great Eſteem for their Perſeverance, I ſhould be very much troubled to incur their Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Farewel, Sir, you know I am yours, <hi>ad Aras &amp; Focos.</hi> The reſt by the Porter. — <hi>Paris,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
